Guide to the Emma Thursby Papers 1706-1942 (Bulk 1860-1940) MS 2530
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Financial Papers, 1706-1919
  A few financial papers of Emma Thursby's parents and sisters are also part of this series. A bill for the initial purchases of Jane and John Thursby for their home after their marriage is included. Bills for household goods and some small loan documentation are in the folder, "Financial Papers: Thursby, Jane B. and John B," as are ledgers detailing the daily pay of John B. Thursby's employees. These materials document the kinds of mercantile transactions common in Williamsburgh and Bushwick during the middle of the nineteenth century, as well as create an idea of the costs involved in running the class of household Jane Thursby attempted.
  Financial papers of the Van Cott and Bennet families, Emma Thursby's maternal grandparents and relatives, are included in this series. These papers date from as early as 1706 and contain receipts and bills of sale, examples of quotidian life from Williamsburgh and Bushwick, Brooklyn, New York. Two indentures and a pardon have been separated to the oversize folder.
  - Thursby, Emma, 1875-1885 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Thursby, Emma, 1886-1915 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Thursby, Emma, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Thursby, Emma: Account Books, 1875, 1885, 1886, 1879 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Thursby, Alice and Ina, 1885-1891 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Thursby, Jane B. and John B., 1843-1877 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Van Cott/Bennett, 1706-1849 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Account Books, Checkbook Stubs, 1879-1919 (Box 14)
- Series III: Legal Papers, 1788-1903
  Many papers in this series are copies of wills or affidavits of Emma Thursby's family and friends, including Sara Bull, Sarah Farmer, Erminia Rudersorff, and Hannah Thursby (Emma's grandmother). There are multiple copies of legal documents relating to the Thursby siblings' right to title to a piece of land in Brooklyn.
  Singing contracts Emma Thursby made with managers or proprietors of a venue are separately foldered. These date from 1877 to 1891, the height of her singing career. Also included are contracts made between managers, such as Maurice Strakosch, and the proprietor of a venue. Documents that include the signature of Emma Thursby, the other party, or both, were considered to be contracts.
  Legal documents from the Van Cott and Bennet families are included here. These include indentures, wills, deeds, and legal papers pertaining to guardianship. As with the financial papers of these families, they are records of family affairs in early Brooklyn. Some of these materials are oversized; most date from the Eighteenth century.
  - Thursby, Emma: Legal Documents, 1828-1903 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Thursby, Emma: Singing Contracts, 1877-1891 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Thursby family: Legal Documents, 1859-1881 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Van Cott/Bennett Legal Documents, 1788-1805 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Address Books, Diaries, Engagement Books, 1868-1929
  Emma Thursby did not keep any narrative diaries, but logged her activities, callers, and monetary expenses in many small bound engagement books throughout her life. Many of these books exist for a singular year; it is difficult to determine exactly how she utilized each book (for example, although some of the account books consist solely of lists of accounts; similar lists appear in other books from the same year.) Emma Thursby also owned many address books. Some of these are marked with a certain city, for example, "Boston," in which those named inside live. Others are less segregated.
  A case was made for 57 of the smaller diaries, which date from 1868 to 1929, and embossed with the words "Emma Thursby Diaries." Forty-one other small bound books, including engagement books and address books have been housed in a similar sized box. Seventeen engagement books with paper covers (which run from 1900 to 1916) have been housed in pamphlet folders in a separate box with a large diary from 1898.
  - Engagement Books, 1898-1916 (Box 10)
  - Address and Engagement Books, 1886-1922 (Box 14)
  - Emma Thursby Diaries, 1868-1929 (Box 15)
- Series V: Awards, Ephemera, Notes, 1850-1936
  This series contains awards presented to Emma Thursby, ephemera and memorabilia belonging to Emma and her family, and handwritten notes. Paper awards Emma Thursby received from many clubs and organizations are included here; many copies exist of one award presented to her by the Association des Artistes Musiciens, in 1879. The folder 'Handwritten Notes' includes Emma Thursby's reminiscences.
  Emma Thursby's ephemera include menus, placecards, the program from a concert given by Jenny Lind in 1850, and a drawing of her tombstone. The "Keepsake Album" was given to Emma by her father during her time at the Moravian Seminary; the Music Notebook contains lists of song titles and song lyrics. Memorabilia belonging to Ina Thursby also includes menus and placecards, as well as lists of correspondents and clippings. Memorabilia belonging to John B. Thursby consists of his 1859 passport and business cards.
  - Awards and Honors, 1871-1936 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Keepsake Album, 1859 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Music Notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Thursby, Emma, Ephemera, 1850-1931 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Thursby, Ina Notes/Ephemera, 1903-1934 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Thursby, John B. Ephemera, 1859 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Thursby, Emma, Handwritten Notes, 1890-1925 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Subject and Biographical Information, 1879-1938
  This series contains newspaper and magazine clippings, correspondence from Thursby pupils, poetry dedicated to Emma Thursby, albums, lists of concerts given, pamphlets, magazines, and steamliner passenger lists.
  Material in this series did not conform to the other series, or was originally separated at the time of accession (such as the correspondence and clippings files of Emma Thursbys' successful pupils).
  - Subseries 1: Emma Thursby, 1880-1936
    This subseries contains both personal and career-related material. Newspaper clippings of reviews of Emma Thursby's performances are included. The folders pertaining to some of Emma Thursby's most successful pupils include correspondence, programs, and clippings of announcements and reviews. A typed list of attendees at Emma Thursby's Friday salons is included, as is a handwritten list of her 1891 engagements (a complete listing of each concert given by Emma Thursby can be found in Gipson's biography.)
    The 'Clippings' folder contains clippings about Emma Thursby. 'Biographical Notes' consist of typed and handwritten biographical details. Notes on musical education and voice training, including drawings of scales and transcription of songs, are housed separately. Emma Thursby possessed a Russian amulet, given to her by Emilia Rudersdorff, which was lost in 1919. Sketches of the amulet and information about its origins and loss are included here.
    After Emma Thursby's death, Ina Thursby worked hard to assure that her sister's memory would be preserved. She organized a radio broadcast of tributes to Emma on what would have been Emma's 90th birthday, and commissioned a mosaic to be created in memory of Emma. This mosiac, which featured St. Cecilia, the patron saint of music and Emma's namesake, was donated to and installed at the Brooklyn Museum of Art. Information and clippings about both ventures is included in this series.
    - Biographical Information, 1899-1933 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Brooklyn Museum Mosiac, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Engagements, 1891 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Performances of Emma Thursby, Clippings, 1907-1922 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Performances of Emma Thursby, Critiques, 1880-1881 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Pupils. Emory, Rita Cornet, 1902-1927 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Pupils. Green Peggy/Princess Viggo, 1924-1932 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Pupils. Harris, Estelle, 1900-1924 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Pupils. Reddish, Meta (1 of 2), 1907-1936 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Pupils. Reddish, Meta (2 of 2), 1907 -1936 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Pupils. Schaffer, Josephine, 1903 -1914 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Pupils. Wittkowska, Martha, 1903 -1931 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Radio Broadcast, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Russian Amulet, 1907-1919 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Salons, Attendees, 1897-1923 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Voice Training/ Teaching Notes, 1910-1921 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Thursby Family, 1880-1938
    This subseries includes information about Emma Thursby's immediate and extended families and pets. 'Geneological Information' includes information on Thursby, Van Cott, and Bennett family ancestors. Much of the Thursby information comes from the Thursby family members in England whom Emma met during her time there in 1878.
    The Mynah bird material includes an issue of The Phrenological Journal and Phrenological Magazine with an article about Emma and the mynah bird in which it was purported that the two had similar shaped skulls; thus accounting for their musical exploits. It also includes information about how to care for the bird and a letter from the Pullman's Palace Car Company giving permission for the bird to travel on the train with Emma Thursby.
    - Mynah Bird, 1889-1899 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Thursby Biographical Information, 1880-1938 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Thursby Genealogical Information, 1905-1932 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 3: Other Subjects, 1879-1937
    Other subjects are based on large amounts of information and clippings compiled by Emma or Ina on important subjects to them; some of these subjects were originally housed in their own envelopes upon accession.
    Folders are devoted to Emma Thursby's close friends Ole Bull and Sarah Farmer. The material on Sarah Farmer also includes correspondence pertaining to Ms. Farmer's illness in the 1910s, and subsequent attempts to raise money to continue the colony Green Acre in Eliot, Maine. Material devoted specifically to Green Acre, such as programs of lectures and clippings, are housed separately. A blueprint of the Green Acre property is housed in the oversize folder.
    The folder 'Old Brooklyn' contains mainly clippings about and sketches of churches Emma Thursby attended or was engaged by early in her career. A separate folder is dedicated to items pertaining to Henry Ward Beecher, the pastor of Plymouth Church in Brooklyn. This includes information on Beecher, and his church after the time of his pastorship. The folder entitled 'Clippings' contains information about friends of Emma Thursby, and other articles that do not fall under a more specific heading.
    Emma Thursby spent much of the later part of her life engaged with inquiries into philosophy and religion, as evidenced by her support of and attendance at Green Acre programs and lectures, as well as her correspondence and friendship with the Swami Vivekananda. Notes taken by Emma from lectures given by Vivekananda, as well as clippings on pertinent topics and pamphlets detailing Eastern religious philosophies, are included in this series. Some of Emma's notes describe yogic practices of breathing, others are transcriptions of prayers.
    Many amateur poets were inspired by Emma Thursby, judging from the volume of poetry found in the collection. As well as those poems directly dedicated to her, Emma collected clippings of poems from newspapers and magazines, and copied other poems herself. These are all collected here.
    - Beecher, Henry Ward/Plymouth Church, 1911-1937 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Bull, Ole, 1901-1909 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Clippings re various subjects, 1892-1931 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - East Indian Philosophies, 1883-1937 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - East Indian Philosophies, 1883-1937 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Farmer, Sarah, 1901-1914 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Green Acre, 1891-1911 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Herald of Life, 1892-1894 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - "Old Brooklyn"-re: churches of Brooklyn, 1908-1937 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Poetry, 1879-1925 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Autographs, 1875-1910
  Contains loose autographs and a bound autograph book, which was a gift to Emma Thursby from her father. Many loose autographs were found throughout the collection; some are the signatures of letters that have been cut up, others are more traditional signatures on small pieces of paper.
  - Autographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Autograph Book, 1875-1910 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Series VIII: Master Recordings of the Emma Thursby Musicale, 1940
  Box 16 is labeled '14 Master Recordings of the Proceedings at the Emma Thursby musicale given at the New-York Historical Society, December 29, 1940 to honor her memory' and contains 14 metal LPs marked #5226 -- #5238A.
  - 14 Master Recordings of the Proceedings of the Emma Thursby Musicale given at the New-York Historical Society, 1940 December 29 (Box 16)
- Series IX. Programs, Press Clippings and Other Print Matter, 1859-1942
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds programs and press clippings, primarily related to the career of Emma Thursby. Clippings also relate to her death, the publication of Richard McCandless Gipson's biography of Thursby, and fashion exhibitions held at N-YHS and at Bonwit Teller in connection with the book's release.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged roughly by format.
  - Programs, 1866-1878 (Offsite-box 17)
  - Programs, 1879-1882 (Offsite-box 18)
  - Programs, 1883-1908 (Offsite-box 19)
  - Press notices [Clippings] (2 volumes), 1859-1886 (Offsite-box 20)
  - Press notices [Clippings] (2 volumes), 1886-1937 (Offsite-box 21)
  - Press notices [Clippings] (2 volumes), 1877-1891 (Offsite-box 22)
  - Various documents, 1847-1942 (Offsite-box 23)
    This box holds the following:
    * A copy of Richard McCandless Gipson's "Life of Emma Thursby," slipcased, inscribed by Gipson to Roger [Wentworth], 1940.
    * Scrapbook re: "Dedication of the Emma Cecilia Thursby Memorial Hall, Cocoa, Florida, February 21, 1942."
    * Various biographical sketches, programs, pictorial works, circa 1879-1931.
    * Scrapbook of clippings, inscribed to Thursby as "a souvenir of Boston and the Triennial Festival" from A. Parker Browne, May 31, 1877.
    * Many letters and postcards of acknowledgement from various libraries re: the copy of Gipson's book donated to them by Ina Thursby, 1942.
    * "The Opera Chorus Book" by Edward L. White and John E. Gould, 1847. Cover embossed "John B. Thursby."
    * Calling cards, business cards, small notes, invitations, circa 1879 and later, most undated.
  - Clippings, 1894-1930s (Offsite-box 24)
    This box holds:
    * Packets of loose clippings, some noted as duplicates, mostly concerning Thursby's death and post-mortem 1941 fashion show at Bonwit Teller.
    * Loose clippings and ephemera labeled "Pupils."
    * "A singer's story." A series of articles by Clara Louise Kellogg-Strakorsch published in the Saturday Evening Post, 1913.
    * 2 accordion files of clippings, labelled: "Music and Musicians" and "Misc People and Things." circa 1900s-1930s.
    * Scrapbook of clippings principally concerning Mrs. Milward Adams, of Chicago, an advocate of voice training for women, 1894-98.
  - Press notices re: Gipson's "Life of Emma Thursby" and related (2 volumes), 1938-1942 (Offsite-box 25)
    2 volumes:
    1) One was a gift of Richard M. Gipson, March 19, 1948. This volume has clippings about the book and a related dress exhibition at N-YHS, ephemera related to the book's release, and photographs of the related fashion exhibition at Bonwit Teller.
    2) The second volume was embossed as belonging to Ina Thursby. It was donated by her estate, February 1, 1944. This album principally holds clippings about Gipson's book and the fashion exhibitions.